{
  "title": "Engineering_Mathematics - Engineering_Mathematics — Slot 13 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Engineering_Mathematics — Slot 13",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements applies to the bisection method used for finding roots of functions: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>converges within a few iterations</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>guaranteed to work for all continuous functions</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>is faster than the Newton-Raphson method</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>requires that there be no error in determining the sign of the function</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>guaranteed to work for all continuous functions</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1640/gate1998-1-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following set of equations<br>\n\\(x+2y=5\\\\ 4x+8y=12\\\\ 3x+6y+3z=15\\)<br>\nThis set <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>has unique solution</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>has no solution</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>has finite number of solutions</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>has infinite number of solutions</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>has no solution</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1639/gate1998-1-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The trapezoidal method to numerically obtain \\(\\int_a^b f(x) dx\\) has an error \\(E\\) bounded by \\(\\frac{b-a}{12} h^2 \\max f''(x), x \\in [a, b]\\) where \\(h\\) is the width of the trapezoids. The minimum number of trapezoids guaranteed to ensure \\(E \\leq 10^{-4}\\) in computing \\(\\ln 7\\) using \\(f=\\frac{1}{x}\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>60</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>100</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>600</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>10000</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>600</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2251/gate1997-4-10\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>A polynomial p(x) is such that p(0)=5,p(1)=4,p(2)=9 and p(3)=20. The minimum degree it should have is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2245/gate1997-4-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Using the forward Euler method to solve \\(y''(t) = f(t), y'(0)=0\\) with a step size of \\(h\\), we obtain the following values of \\(y\\) in the first four iterations: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(0, hf (0), h(f(0) + f(h)) \\text{ and }h(f(0) - f(h) + f(2h))\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(0, 0, h^2f(0)\\text{ and } 2h^2 f(0) + f(h)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(0, 0, h^2f(0) \\text{ and } 3h^2f(0)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(0, 0, hf(0) + h^2f(0) \\text{ and }hf (0) + h^2f(0) + hf(h)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(0, 0, hf(0) + h^2f(0) \\text{ and }hf (0) + h^2f(0) + hf(h)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2244/gate1997-4-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(A=(a_{ij})\\) be an n-rowed square matrix and \\(I_{12}\\) be the matrix obtained by interchanging the first and second rows of the n-rowed Identity matrix. Then \\(AI_{12}\\) is such that its first <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Row is the same as its second row</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Row is the same as the second row of A</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Column is the same as the second column of A</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Row is all zero</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Column is the same as the second column of A</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2243/gate1997-4-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>What is the maximum value of the function \\(f(x) = 2x^2 - 2x + 6\\) in the interval \\(\\left[0,2 \\right]\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>12</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>5.5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>10</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2242/gate1997-4-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>The determinant of the matrix \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 6 &amp; -8 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \\\\ 0 &amp; 2 &amp; 4 &amp; 6 \\\\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 4 &amp; 8 \\\\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; -1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>11</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>-48</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>-24</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>-48</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2219/gate1997-1-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>The Newton-Raphson method is used to find the root of the equation \\(X^2-2=0\\). If the iterations are started from -1, the iterations will <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>converge to -1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>converge to \\(\\sqrt{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>converge to \\(\\sqrt{-2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>not converge</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>converge to \\(\\sqrt{-2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2218/gate1997-1-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The matrices \\(\\begin{bmatrix} \\cos\\theta &amp;&amp; -\\sin\\theta \\\\ \\sin\\theta &amp;&amp; \\cos\\theta \\end{bmatrix}\\) and \\(\\begin{bmatrix} a &amp;&amp; 0\\\\ 0&amp;&amp; b \\end{bmatrix}\\) commute under multiplication <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>if \\(a=b \\text{ or } \\theta = n\\pi\\), n is an integer</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>always</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>never</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>if \\(a \\cos\\theta = b \\sin\\theta\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>if \\(a=b \\text{ or } \\theta = n\\pi\\), n is an integer</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2735/gate1996-2-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Newton-Raphson iteration formula for finding \\(\\sqrt[3]{c}\\), where c &gt; 0 is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(x_{n+1}=\\frac{2x_n^3 + \\sqrt[3]{c}}{3x_n^2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(x_{n+1}=\\frac{2x_n^3 - \\sqrt[3]{c}}{3x_n^2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(x_{n+1}=\\frac{2x_n^3 + c}{3x_n^2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(x_{n+1}=\\frac{2x_n^3 - c}{3x_n^2}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(x_{n+1}=\\frac{2x_n^3 + c}{3x_n^2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2734/gate1996-2-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Let AX = b be a system of linear equations where A is an \\(m \\times n\\) matrix and b is a \\(m \\times 1\\) column vector and X is an \\(n \\times 1\\) column vector of unknowns. Which of the following is false? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The system has a solution if and only if, both A and the augmented matrix [Ab] have the same rank.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>If m &lt; n and b is the zero vector, then the system has infinitely many solutions.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>If m=n and b is a non-zero vector, then the system has a unique solution.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The system will have only a trivial solution when m=n, b is the zero vector and rank (A) =n.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>If m=n and b is a non-zero vector, then the system has a unique solution.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2711/gate1996-1-7\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>The formula used to compute an approximation for the second derivative of a function \\(f\\) at a point \\(x_0\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{f(x_0 +h) + f(x_0 - h)}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{f(x_0 +h) - f(x_0 - h)}{2h}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{f(x_0 +h) + 2f(x_0) + f(x_0 - h)}{h^2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{f(x_0 +h) - 2f(x_0) + f(x_0 - h)}{h^2}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{f(x_0 +h) - 2f(x_0) + f(x_0 - h)}{h^2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2710/gate1996-1-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>The solution of differential equation \\(y''+3y'+2y=0\\) is of the form <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(C_1e^x+C_2e^{2x}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(C_1e^{-x}+C_2e^{3x}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(C_1e^{-x}+C_2e^{-2x}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(C_1e^{-2x}+C_2e^{-x}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(C_1e^{-x}+C_2e^{-2x}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2630/gate1995-2-18\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>The iteration formula to find the square root of a positive real number b using the Newton Raphson method is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(x_{k+1} = 3(x_k+b)/2x_k\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(x_{k+1} = (x_{k}^2+b)/2x_k\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(x_{k+1} = x_k-2x_k/\\left(x^2_k+b\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(x_{k+1} = (x_{k}^2+b)/2x_k\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2627/gate1995-2-15\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}